all right welcome to the first weekly
game be idea cafe this week's question
is what does game be mean to me you will
each take up to five minutes
to answer that question and then have an
open discussion about what everyone
else's answers generated for us who
would like to start I can go ahead and
start I know do believe started a lot of
these yeah although I don't I don't have
a whole bunch to say I got interested in
the game B concept because I would like
to spend more time helping other helping
other people in a exponential way and so
some of the concepts in there seem to be
you know kind of anti rival risks and
you know having everyone contribute some
of those ideas I found interesting and
had been you know aligning with some of
the stuff I've been working on for the
last couple years of group discussion so
I kind of see it as a way to kind of be
more participatory and kind of taking a
look at how we're doing things and in
the broader sense like society and the
world and culturally and what are some
things that we want to keep and order
some things that we want to experiment
on to try to improve that's it should
probably unlike myself first or I mute
myself it's funny for I was looking down
getting the timer ready while you were
talking minute alright we're not Eric
and to welcome Eric I think Eric if you
put on some headphones we're getting an
echo I don't know if you can all right
do you want to go next friend so do want
me to go next you go ahead all right
excuse me everybody else and start my
own reset go all right
game B what does it mean to me it means
everything as I have already in my head
come up with the way that we dismantle
capitalism and create a new world that
works for everyone and how we do that
from a space of out competing game a on
its own turf that it has to come out of
gaming and it has to do better than game
a and be safe enough to try and that all
happened before I encountered game B in
September and now having people who
speak that language even though I didn't
know the language of Omni win of and
even if I disagree that you know they
want to like tape we take a lot of steps
back and do all the interpersonal work
that I feel like I've been doing and yet
I still need people to do that with I
don't think you can figure it all out in
isolation and I'd already kind of let go
of my idea in a way that it doesn't have
to be mine it doesn't have to be this
way
but to recreate something together that
brings individual autonomy that's never
about the individual giving up their
power to the group but is about a bunch
of autonomous people coming together
creating something creating the tools
they need to be able to work in smaller
groups for the benefit of themselves the
benefit of the group and the benefit of
the entire whole and we all get to
benefit in in those pieces and so that
is what game B is to me it's Omni win
solutions it's looking at our own
individual lives and figuring out why
and how being raised within game a what
part of that is efficient water what
part of that is like how am I being
rivalries how am i how do I create Omni
win solutions when there's a part of me
that wants to compete when there's a
part of me that wants to do better have
more and there's the logical part that
also knows I have that I'm gonna get
what everyone else has to give and the
more I give and the more they give and
not required everyone give up all of
themselves and become a selfless human
being that's basically entered a cult
how to put a toe in the water be like
how do we cooperate a little bit more
how do we see the benefit of that and
the
the enjoyment it brings individually so
it grows and how do you work with two
people Bentley and me creating the idea
cafe and then how do you bring more
people on board and have it work and how
do you how do you have a conversation
and a system to create things with
dozens of people hundreds of people
thousands of people and eventually
billions of people that is effective and
actually works but still isn't the
billions having control over those even
the one how do you keep bringing that
and it is the individual the group the
global all at once and a lot of that can
be done or started with the tools on
technology which is why that is what I'm
concentrating on and I'm also not going
to take five minutes because I feel like
that was a lot and I'm going on mic
everyone else can go next
alright Brent or Eric would either of
you like to go next
I'll go I guess hmm I think of game B in
terms of a paradigm shift which which is
both sort of an overused term but also
underrated because if you take it
seriously it makes it more difficult to
kind of you know prove the paradigm
shift and precisely locate it and that's
what we're trying to do right and also
something like revolutions happen quite
often in a global context and and
historically they're kind of you know
marching forward or backwards depending
on the type but that's the difference
here between a revolution in the
paradigm shift like if they they
definitely will coincide like I think
the US needs a political revolution um
but but a paradigm shift is when
everything changes like the scientific
paradigm being the kind of cultural
zeitgeist all these sorts of things so
mm-hmm
I think I think there's some flaws with
the game a game be framing it's it can
be overly simplistic but it's also
salient in the sense that like if we say
okay everything historically is game a
because it's kind of brought us to this
point like capitalism communism war mm
um is kind of gay game a the way we've
kind of unconsciously
developed as a civilization then we
recognize we have to change you know
because of like as from October gir
unpacks things like generator functions
these things that are built-in to
creating the pathologies down the road
I've got this this concept I developed I
didn't invent the term but I but it's
not very well defined in the literature
so I wrote an article on social
paradoxes it's called social paradoxes
and meta problems and and I think this
also kind of captures what we're talking
about and and like with generator
functions because a lot of the
pathologies are built into the decisions
we make even if it's just consumption or
you know how you know population growth
whatever its kind of built in so to
overcome paradoxes and especially social
paradoxes is incredibly complex and
difficult right like it's that's why
they're paradoxes so meaning there are
strategies to to overcome them one is
called normative incremental ism where
you have kind of values that you that
you uh kind of set as attractors and
then agree to work together towards that
so I think you know I I guess as much
that's as much as I want to say in a
nutshell of about it but I'll repeat
that like I said in a previous cafe mmm
I I come I come to this community of
from a perspective of thinking about
Mehta modernism and that kind of
paradigm shift from from postmodern post
modernism and post modernity as opposed
to kind of coming into it getting
through through Brett Weinstein and and
and his perspectives but I think I think
there's furfle potential to you don't
see how these things converge and we can
actually you know
a day-by-day work work through this
paradigm shift Thank You Brent all right
Eric would you like to go or would you
like to just have a discuss so I'll see
how much I can remember so the idea of
paradigm shift I have to agree with that
but I think you sort of alluded we're
answering the question what does game be
mean to me and then after we'll have a
conversation okay it was it was kind of
okay so what is going be mean to me I
don't get I guess fundamentally at its
base game B is what it is among other
things what game a is not so if game a
is foundationally characterized by
people competing with each other for
advantage in some way whether that be
rethought status wealth whatever it
might be
but the game a is fundamentally
characterized by their game B is
collaborative cooperative on rival way
so the other
the other thing that it means to me is
that it's it's and this is the big
appeal for me is that it's built on
something which to me seems meaningful
solid namely good people sovereign
individual and and and that again and
again and again know people who I admire
can't be returned 'ti I'm bad and the
people that brought me to it affirmed
this again and again and again and again
sitting around and talk about one thing
but they're doing it and something which
slightly bothers me about Wayne way game
spoken back by her questions about and
but you know after game be then maybe
game see you know because game be you
think about game being that way it's
just another structure of some kind it
may be a different structure but it's
just another structure at some point and
so game be for me is
flexible space which acknowledges the
things change all the time right special
moves leading with the complex things
change time and so game B is not about
putting a different structure into base
more flexible structures more adept
structure it if the thing which allows
the formation and dissolution of
structures as they are necessary and
then later become unnecessary or
outdated or have been improved upon in
some way whatever and so it's a it's a
meta thing it's not a thing it's a it's
a it's a better thing in that thing I
wrote I don't know if any ready I sort
of alluded to it like that dowel right
it's a formless nameless thing it's a
it's characterized by certain feelings
of
not poisoning the well in any way not
just in your interpersonal relationships
but in the broader relationship with
with nature in the cosmos at large yes
sir that knot was wealthy have I gone on
too long already
I'm I'm kind of into a kind of onto a
runaway flown so yeah is that the game B
to me is about a set of emotions and
feelings kind of but the emotions maybe
the wrong word but principles and values
which are not set in stone
again they couldn't really be spoken but
it's a it's a apart connection is a part
of it well okay I'm going to stop there
all right your mic was cutting not in
and out but like quieter louder a lot
while I was we were listening so
hopefully that's within within that also
um Brett your chair is squeaking I don't
know if everyone else but I'm just
sensitive to sound
myself when I'm not talking all right
sounds good
all right and other than that we can
have an an open discussion for now what
game being what other people said that
resonated with us and what it what it
brought up as I'm saying before the
paradigm shift idea that phrase used but
again kind of alluding to what I was
saying in the doctoral bit it's not
really a different paradigm it's more
the ability to install and uninstall
appropriate paradigms for that thing for
that modality whatever's like trans
paradigm attic know what I mean what it
is to me though that this is what it is
to me I see you nodding would you agree
with that idea yeah I think there's a
place for that approach we do have to
think of this in terms of um you know
whether it's switching paradigms or
intermingling paradigms without
compromising right so there's a big
difference between conscious capitalism
and post capitalism as concepts as
discourses so I think you know there's
there's a role for trans paradigm attic
thinking and and met a paradigmatic for
sure because there are it's not always
as clear as okay there's one paradigm
and now there's a you know now there's a
new one like from you know mmm you know
geocentric to heliocentric it's not
always that clear so like the the term
paradigm can be used loosely if you if
you you know Google Scholar search it
sometimes paradigm shift will be used in
lots of different subfields like oh
there's a paradigm shift in you know
cardiovascular medicine it's like really
specific thing and that's obviously not
what I'm
you know yeah I don't even know if I
know what a paradigm shift really is to
be able to it like that it isn't
something that's just like today we're
under capitalism tomorrow we're not like
it's it's looking back and realizing
that you have that ten years twenty
years thirty years later there's been a
huge change and then the kind of looking
back and labeling that and why did it
happen and I think a lot of us can feel
were in that we are in very rapid change
whether for the better for the worse and
need to come up with ways to work within
human nature to work on solutions even
if we're not getting along to work on
holding holding powers the wrong word
but like taking power back from the tiny
few who have it and you're spreading it
out so that we have power over our own
lives in power over our the things that
directly impact our everyday lives or in
our healthcare or transportation the
things that we use and under capitalism
we do in a way we get to choose where we
put our dollar but without actually
living in capitalism like it's founded
on the economics that we all have
perfect knowledge and work in logical
ways when we neither have perfect
knowledge nor work in logical ways and
so creating systems that just keep
asking like why are we doing what we're
doing and how do we improve it and
without ever requiring you do anything
just because I think you should if I
want you to do the thing how do I
empower you to do the thing including
you might never do it because you might
it might not be in alignment with what
you want to do and I have to kind of
figure it out I don't require other
people to you to the thing so yeah I've
I was I guess I had two thoughts based
upon hearing you guys one is well let me
skip one oh so we don't quite know what
game B is we know what it isn't because
it's not certain aspects of game a that
we think have negative consequences and
aren't aren't law
term viable are my understand this game
B's been around for a while are we
actually making progress towards an
understanding or are we going to be in a
perpetual we don't want to define game B
because then it becomes something that
has harder edges I would say that some
people have more clear developed ideas
about this then they lead on or they're
frank about it like Daniel schmock and
Berger and Jordan Hall you know they
kind of lead the conversation in a sense
but I think they're doing a kind of
social experiment to to you know get you
know to see how we can talk about this
right it's kind of a an extension of the
IDW conversational practice if you
consider that a kind of prototype for
better better or worse that you know for
this to succeed at scale you know we we
wanted to kind of develop it as a
community not just a few people but as a
kind of co-creative generative process
the generation functions I did we don't
know what game he is I heard Jordan
talking about this gym rats podcast
always always be thinking game his going
time many of us because of the
prevalence they may be playing game he
hit zero level but you know that's
that's all it's our baseline right so
that you know game be supposed to return
to how we were rather than it being
anything fundamentally new so again it's
it's a it's a grounded sense of
interconnectedness I think that the very
very heart of it if you do have an
embodied sense and lived sense of
interconnectedness with other people
you simply cannot behave in many of the
ways behaving game what I mean
that has to be the that has to be the
foundation of it and did the systems
change yeah the the tech stuff Springs
must spring from that you know that's
art and everything else must spring from
that for me that's that's so I I have a
concern about that is that in most of
what I do every day it's it's game a and
I don't think that I can make that
transition to that feeling of game B as
long as I'm being bombarded by game a
because I have to I you know during the
day I have to defend myself I have to I
have to compete to make money to survive
to get food I have to compete so if I
don't have some tech or some safe space
I don't think I can keep that essence of
game B in my brain for very long
yeah I think that's a really helpful
point Bentley I think like everybody has
to be aware aware of that um I know uh
Jubilee is on disability so am I so that
actually enables us to opt out of game a
quite easily I mean it's hard for me to
participate in game a uh
you know roughly speaking uh cuz I I
mean this is it's been it's been a
challenge for many many years but it got
to a point where I just couldn't like
write a cover letter
I couldn't apply for a job I couldn't do
a job if I had one mm-hmm and you know
it's very connected to this discourse
this embodiment this ecology of
practices right you get to a point where
you just can't do it anymore and and
your choices then are to you know die
and be homeless or if you're lucky
you'll get support and then you can you
can kind of commit yourself to it and
say okay I'm not going back I don't have
to go you know oh I'll get by on a
disability income
and try to you know make money in the
gig economy you know hopping from from
gig to gig if it's ethical if it's
interesting right otherwise then you
know I can say no or not I'm not
qualified or whatever so that's an
important point it seems to be to me
that the people who I guess there's
three groups of people creating game be
is those who have somewhat one at game a
those who have the money and the power
and the ability much like Jordan Jordan
Hall and Brett Brett Wayne Weinstein and
and such that the I mean they have
enough of the the backing that they
don't have to compete in game Akon so
they're competing in game a but they
have more freedoms as now compete with
in game be people like I'm assuming
Bentley who are like right I have to
work a job I have to fit this in between
and find space to make that more viable
and then people like Brent and I who
have kind of lost game a right like
health-wise I can tell I'm never gonna
compete in game a I'm never gonna win
that and with people like Jordan
Peterson or like well if you just tap
into your ingenuity I'm like you don't
know what my might like you don't know
what I've been through you don't know
what it's like to have your mind changed
like literally like have your brain have
damage to it that you can't do what you
used to do but in tapping into instead
of can I compete in game a what do I
have to contribute that's a compliment
is Omni win everybody has something to
contribute everybody and then the more
work able to contribute as individuals
the more is a collective we have more
and more to gain and so I think it's
important to not to allow all three of
those groups to you know that like
there's those of us who may not have the
financial capability but we have time
and we have our own ideas and we have a
certain amount to contribute because
we're losing game a and there's people
who have the opposite who are winning a
game a have the power have the money to
contribute and if they're winning at it
so they can't see all the broken pieces
as easily as people who maybe aren't
winning at it is my understanding right
now
well if I can talk because I was gonna
take the discussion in a different
direction so if you want to talk about
well I was just I was just gonna jump
back what you said about keeping the
spirit of game be alive play game a day
right and I think as Brent said it's
very valid this is also we can't get
into until it has to all happen at once
you know what I mean that until the
whole world is is like that then you
know there's there's always this
conflict it's been game a and game B
until unless the sudden flip and
everybody goes at once so this is always
what makes the idea of transition so
very very very difficult because you
have this tension between these two
fundamentally but it just made me think
of the you know yeah you can see what
the problems are you can see what the
solutions are how you get from here to
there is the impossible bit right you
know you must've heard the same thing
yourself a million times right and just
and I think that is part of why that is
such a big problem individual on
Facebook right sorry no that's good
that's good
yeah and that's I guess that's where I
kind of focus is what's what are these
kind of small steps and that's why
Jubilee and I are kind of working on the
tech side even though a lot of people
think that that's kind of premature
we're just trying to give ourselves some
space and maybe find me and income kind
of building an experiment for game B on
some of the concepts that we know so far
but I was also thinking you know you
talk about the the feeling that it is
and that it is and I think Brent when
you're saying paradigm changes not just
a societal paradigm change it's a
paradigm change within each individual
and I think someone is doing some
training on that to kind of help people
make that transition are there any other
active
things in activities that are happening
in the game bSpace that are building
that emotional state or safe space I
mean like this is hopefully but I'm
involved it's Eric and I are meeting
tomorrow with a group of people to
practice a mega rule and practice and
him and I are meeting to do circling
which i think is very the more we can
create the tech that supports those kind
of things because you can zoom but the
more that we're benefiting from that we
can transport it or you know offer it in
a way that it's easy for people to come
on board right where they might not be
able to be part of the conversation
we're having because there's five of us
right that kind of is the the point
where we you know we don't want more
people joining that conversation
necessarily but to be able to join their
own conversations yes I want to practice
I'll make a rule right where are my
people to practice it with and the more
we can create the technology that makes
that easier which is I think what we're
concentrating on on the idea cafe is
like how you bring people together how
you get that scheduling piece right how
you get the underlining tech piece right
to meet people where they're at right
that it's hard to sometimes get people
together it's a little bit vulnerable to
put yourself out there and ask hey is
anyone interested in this and creating
that that piece of it yeah so we have so
it kind of the activities going on is we
have we have these and then we have
you're talking about practicing the
Omega rule I don't know I guess I'd like
to see a list of all that is kind of the
the onboarding piece that's still a bit
of a challenge is it not to a certain
extent anyway up to big grid out so you
know again the things like rule Omega
and certain these are practices to build
capacities at an individual group level
right which can then be applied out in
by the world as hopefully as both
Aerodyne shift in more and more and more
individual so I yeah you two you guys
are focusing on the tech which is
essential don't get me wrong I'm not
downplaying it's not my thing me
it's that this is all about building my
capacity at a selfish level but also
engaging in the process of collectively
building path to a and understand and
open mind and see things have no job but
and so on and so on I can understand a
lot of what you're saying Eric because
of the mic I don't know if anyone else's
is having the same the same level of
problems but I think a lot of what
you're saying is important but it
doesn't quite register because of that
in a note that is kind of hard and yeah
I don't know if you got a loose cable or
something but it's kind of fading in and
out but I think I got most of it yeah
before I was and now it's getting light
but in the highest and lows or like it's
cutting out in the lows for me on my
ends but yeah no no it's gone we're also
we're coming to the ends of the ideas
for you Sydney around 30 minutes so that
we can um schedule a more afterwards
what we can do generally speaking is we
stop recording and then we go unlive so
that we can then vote on whether or not
we want to publish it or delete it or
keep it private or what however we want
to do that and we can also continue the
conversation but I'll give everyone a
chance to wrap up to say there are
closing thoughts before we stop
recording on the same orders before okay
oh and I really appreciated hearing
everyone's opinions I've been very
curious about that because game B is so
amorphous right now and that's a
difficult space for me I like boundaries
and they make me feel safe and rules but
I'll be you know learning kind of all of
this all the felt stuff and growing in
that space
and then I kind of look forward to a day
where I can be less competitive in
having to fund myself so kind of I kind
of hopefully get this rolling
I mean I met a really good work
environment and I'm not competitive on a
day-to-day basis in that but when I try
about hat thinking about having more
time to donate to this and I think well
I need to become a contractor so I can
lower my hours and focus more time on
game B and then I'm like well that I'm
really competing if I'm a contractor in
a lot of cases so but I look forward to
hearing more there's a sense in which
you know game B is not not here yet
we're thinking about it in the future
but there's also a lot of concepts out
there or you know and you can say all of
the kind of march of history is kind of
baby steps in that direction
notwithstanding you know the generator
functions and negative externalities
that might destroy us
you know like things like the civil
rights movements are obviously steps in
the right direction but I think there's
a lot of concepts that that you know we
can we can have two columns between game
a and game B II tentatively you know
things like D growth you know post
capitalism a steady state economy you
know there's there's a lot of kind of
conceptual frameworks out there and
we're I think still in the process of
mapping that whole discourse Thank You
Brent you Eric yeah just just just very
quickly the unknown nature of what game
B is don't require the ability to
experiment right those systems right
here's and transitional measures so on
are going to need to be experimental
they roll down so if and I'm averse to
doing this just because I'm way way way
over my personality type
for the nitty-gritty how are we gonna
get that sounds like a very very
starting point is
all right I'm oh and this then I just
wanted to put this up on the screen for
anybody who wants to vote if they
generally you vote if you want to
participate in the conversations and
what question you want to discuss we'll
be doing these for game B idea cafes at
the same same time period every week so
you can get in contact with me if you
want to participate crab dip at crab
democracy on Twitter or in the facebook
group Jubilee and I'm just gonna take
this down because it's covering Eric in
Bentley's face and that my idea for for
game be Ohio just want to wrap it up is
that I do think that we need to have
tools to be able to listen to people on
every level we need to be able to ask
individuals what would build your
capacity to play a game B and then help
create that to help create food system
shelter systems create the basic needs
of necessities if we're not having to
rely on game aid to get them and I don't
think it's a overnight yet there I think
it's like well what are you doing for
food and how do we keep helping you
incrementally put in less labor and less
some money and get your food needs met
and your community needs met and I think
there is a lot and then on it on a group
level what kind of groups do want to be
a part of and how if we facilitate that
with tools and on a mega level how do we
have the the sense making and data that
makes it makes it usable and so to me
all of those things can be done it can
be supported with tech but the
individual piece of creating a better
world and practicing rule Omega is also
very very important and so we'll end
this here we will stop broadcasting and
vote on what to do this